14.3 Fairness.
You will find this in Chapter 4 of the
Code of Ethics and Professional Conduct.
And just a reminder that although this is
examinable, it doesn't
appear in the Pembark guide.
It's available as a free download from the
PMI website, PMI.org.
In fact, if you are a member
of PMI, which you should be,
you can download a heap of
staff free of charge from PMI.
Description of fairness.
Fairness is our duty to make decisions and
act impartially and objectively.
Our conduct must be free from competing
self-interest, prejudice and favouritism.
Fairness, aspirational standards.
As practitioners of the global project
management community, one, we demonstrate
transparency in our decision-making
process.
Two, we constantly re-examine our
impartiality and objectivity.
taking corrective action as
appropriate and you don't have
to raise a change request to
make changes to your behaviour.
Comment, research with practitioners
indicates that the subject of conflicts of
interest is one of the most challenging
faced by our profession.
One of the biggest problems practitioners
report is not recognising that we have
conflicted loyalties and recognising when
we are inadvertently placing ourselves or
others in a conflict of interest
situation.
We as practitioners must proactively
search for potential conflicts and help
each other by highlighting
each other's potential
conflicts of interest and
insisting that they be resolved.
Did you notice it said help
each other by highlighting
each other's potential
conflicts of interest?
It's because sometimes we
really don't actually realize
that we're getting into a
conflict of interest situation.
But other people can
see it and they can advise
us and we can watch out
for them and advise them.
And of course the other times when we sort
of know we're getting into a bad area and
for some reason we're just going with the
flow.
But as they say, it's only dead fish who
go with the flow.
But sometimes you just need a friend to
give you a kick in the seat of the pants
and waking you up and say, what you're
doing is actually wrong?
Okay, number three, We
provide equal access to information
to those who are authorised
to have that information.
I used to have a manager and each time he
went on and you leave, he used to lock up
the manuals which are under
his control so that nobody
could do as good a job as
he could while he was away.
Number four, we make opportunities equally
available to qualified candidates.
Comment and implication of these
provisions, is that in the case of a
contracting arrangement,
we provide equal access
to information during the bidding process.
So we have a friend or a relative who
works for one of the competing contractors.
We don't give them information that the
others don't help.
We don't give them any advantages.
We have to make it a level playing field
for everyone.
Imagine if you're a
contract, you're in the
process, you're trying to get some work.
and you'd discover that
went to a company that was
related in some way to the
person who made the decision.
How would you feel?
So capture those feelings and think, I can
cause the same sort
of problems with others.
Fairness, mandatory standards.
As practitioners in the global project
management community, we require the
following of ourselves and our fellow
practitioners.
Conflicts of interest is situations.
Number one.
actively and fully disclose
any real or potential
conflicts of interest to the
appropriate stakeholders.
My personal advice is if you're not sure
if you're in some sort of conflict of
interest situation, tell people anyway,
let the people decide it then becomes
their decision, you have done the right
thing, you have bed by the code.
Without going into details,
I have been in a couple of
situations before where I
felt this is a conflict of interest.
I've gone to the management, told them
they've gone through the details,
come back to say, we don't see a conflict
of interest, please continue, or there's a
conflict of interest
system, but all you have
to do is don't be on
this particular committee.
So it becomes their decision, so never
hold anything back because it will come
back to bite you when you're least
expecting it.
Number two, when we realize that we have a
real or potential conflict of interest,
we refrain from engaging in the
decision-making process or otherwise
attempting to influence outcomes unless or
until we have made full disclosure to the
affected stakeholders, which is what I
said before.
We have an approved mitigation plan which
means you don't attend certain meetings or
withdraw from the project completely,
whatever it takes, and we have obtained
the consent of the stakeholders to
proceed.
Comment.
A conflict of interest occurs when we are
in a position to influence decisions or
other outcomes on behalf of one party,
when such decisions or outcomes would
affect one or more of the other parties
with which we have competing loyalties.
For example, when we
are acting as an employee,
we have a duty of loyalty to our employer.
When we are acting as a
PMI volunteer, we have a
duty of loyalty to the
Project Management Institute.
You must recognize these divergent
interests and refrain from influencing
decisions when we have a conflict of
interest.
Further, even if we believe that we can
set aside our divided loyalties make
decisions impartially, we treat the
appearance of a conflict of interest as a
conflict of interest and follow the
provisions described in the code.
So, even if there's no certainty it is a
conflict of interest, treat it as a
conflict of interest until you hear
categorically one way or the other.
Favoritism and discrimination three.
We do not hire or fire reward or
punish or reward or deny contracts
based on personal considerations,
including, but not limit.
favoritism, nepotism or bribery.
Four, we did not discriminate against
others based on gender, race, age,
religion, disability, nationality, sexual
orientation, or basically anything else.
In fact, all of these things, if you do
them, they are actually illegal.
But whenever the Pimbok was first drawn up
and they were working on their code of
ethics, The first code
of ethics was just like a
little half a page thing
and it gradually evolved.
But back in the early days, some of this
stuff wasn't actually illegal.
For example, age discrimination is a
fairly recent one to be recognised.
Number five, we apply the rules of the
organisation, the employer, project
management institute or other group
without favour or prejudice.
In other words, you don't go cherry pick.
and I'll use this particular rule,
I'll ignore this one, etc.
to give yourself some sort of benefit.
That brings us to the end of fairness.
And the next lesson is 14.4 honesty.
Please read the corresponding
section of the Code of
Ethics and Professional
Conduct before watching the video.